<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>duckworth.design</title>
  <subtitle>A small design and product consultancy in the UK</subtitle>
  <id>https://duckworth.design/articles</id>
  <link href="https://duckworth.design/articles"/>
  <link href="https://duckworth.design/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2023-01-18T22:29:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The mapping tool we've been using with most of our clients</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://duckworth.design/articles/01/2023/the-mapping-tool-we-ve-been-using-with-most-of-our-clients.html"/>
    <id>https://duckworth.design/articles/01/2023/the-mapping-tool-we-ve-been-using-with-most-of-our-clients.html</id>
    <published>2023-01-18T22:29:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-01-19T10:52:52+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href="https://duckworth.design/"&gt;duckworth.design&lt;/a&gt; we’ve recently been supporting a lot of organisations large and small to map out and understand where they are and where they want to get to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some of these organisations, it’s not for a lack of understanding or insight into problems. It’s the clarity of what to do about those problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 of the teams we’re working with have done 5 years worth of research. But they’ve struggled to make an impact in that area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no single reason for that lack of change. We’re talking about systems and organisations that are very complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a technique that we’ve used quite a bit to help sort out our own thoughts, and structure how these organisations respond and plot what to do next is by using a type of impact mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say we have a snappy name. We don’t. It’s sort of a “problem to solution” impact mapping process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve written it up in &lt;a href="/our-playbook/problem-solution-mapping.html"&gt;our playbook&lt;/a&gt; how to follow it. But effectively it’s about following a chain of questions and generating answers to them. Which, with understanding of your users and context, will help you create a visual thread of the problem you’re seeing, who it impacts, how you’d know you’re improving the issue and what you’re going to do to make that improvement happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../../../images/123.svg" alt="An example impact map. Boxes connect to each other" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do it on your own, in small or large groups. Though it does need a strong sense of your users and their needs. Or the acceptance that you’re working on assumptions that’ll need to be proven. To stop it being a guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go through the process, run through each column to generate and discuss:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statement of what’s happening today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The users impacted by that (internal, external etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The issues caused by what’s happening today for that user (these may overlap)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write statements that explain the positive change or impact you’d see that would come about from a change. For example, spending less time managing help desk requests resetting login details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then for each positive change, generate the many things you could do to make that positive change happen. This could be many things and things that might conflict with each other. That’s okay. You can prioritise or explore desirability and feasibility later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we like about it is how clear it makes moving from a problem statement to solutions. It also ensures that the thread is easy to understand, challenge and prove (or not!). It also helps teams who have some people who are better at solutions and those at identifying needs work together. And link up their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It enables organisations to reflect on the multiple issues being caused by how things work today, as well the multiple actions they could or need to take to resolve issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../../../images/impact-map-example.png" alt="An example of an impact map in use. Small boxes connect to many others. With hundreads of initiatives connecting to each positive outcome" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
(Zoomed out example where we used an earlier version of the tool for a complex data platform team)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For start ups we use a similar model, but focus the “what’s happening today” with a goal, mission or future vision they want to be part of. Rather than a more traditional problem statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This flavour of impact mapping tool has really helped shape the strategy for large organisations and small. And done so where the thread from insights of today can drive the solutions being worked on next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want a bit more detail about how to use it? &lt;a href="/our-playbook/problem-solution-mapping.html"&gt;Find that advice in our playbook&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want us to help shape your product or service&amp;rsquo;s strategy and future? &lt;a href="https://forms.gle/Ssz4tNUnJSkAgVQR6"&gt;Get in touch through our form&lt;/a&gt; or by &lt;a href="mailto:contact@duckworth.design"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Should designers prototype in code?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://duckworth.design/articles/12/2022/should-designers-prototype-in-code.html"/>
    <id>https://duckworth.design/articles/12/2022/should-designers-prototype-in-code.html</id>
    <published>2022-12-20T17:16:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-12-20T17:52:36+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether designers should prototype in HTML (and CSS and JavaScript) often depends on the specific situation and goals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTML can be a useful tool for prototyping because it allows designers to create realistic interactive and functional prototypes. Useful for gathering feedback from potential users and for identifying any potential problems or limitations. And unlike other approaches to prototyping, closer to what the end product will be. And the constraints of the medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also allows designers to simulate as closely to a real experience as possible and as such elicit real frustrations and reactions. That also means that your users will blame themselves rather than your prototype. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be dangerous because it means people will hide frustration. But it&amp;rsquo;s also something HTML prototpyes can illustrate to a team observing real behaviour. That people will think they&amp;rsquo;re doing it wrong. And not raise issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s a good thing to observe to keep yourself and your teams honest. We may not always see or hear issues because we&amp;rsquo;ve seen that users blame themselves rather than our tool. With a bit of storytelling, this can be quite powerful tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But HTML may not always be the best choice. For example, if the prototype doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be interactive or functional, using paper or a visual tool can be a faster and easier way to create a low-fidelity prototype. Additionally, if the prototype needs to be tested on a specific platform or device, using a tool that is specific to that platform or device may be more appropriate. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen lots of prototype testing of paper leaflets and similar with photos on a screen. A print out might be better in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A designer might also not be able to use HTML. Which can slow down and inhibit getting prototypes made. If this is true, find a way to support your designers (or youself) to learn. But maybe don&amp;rsquo;t choose something extremely time pressured to use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, sometimes using HTML or similar means the designer can inhibit themselves by what they&amp;rsquo;re capable of. Not what a skilled team is capable of. Here we&amp;rsquo;re limiting ourselves by our skills not the future possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the decision of whether to prototype in HTML will depend on the specific goals and requirements of a project or team, as well as the designer&amp;rsquo;s personal expertise. The key is to consider what you&amp;rsquo;re trying to achieve, and the best way to get there. And support designers to develop their craft so they have several different ways to prototype. Not just 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, at &lt;a href="www.duckworth.design"&gt;duckworth.design&lt;/a&gt; our designers create prototpyes in code. When it&amp;rsquo;s the right choice. For designers who don&amp;rsquo;t code. We support them to develop that skillset.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Your service maps don't need to look the same</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://duckworth.design/articles/12/2022/your-service-maps-don-t-need-to-look-the-same.html"/>
    <id>https://duckworth.design/articles/12/2022/your-service-maps-don-t-need-to-look-the-same.html</id>
    <published>2022-12-08T10:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-12-20T17:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having worked across many large organisations we’ve often encountered this question. Should there be a uniform style for our blueprints? Typically it’s a thing you see with new designers coming in. Or when people are thinking about design ops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From experience. The reality is, it’s probably the least important thing you can worry about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely is the visual consistency or uniformity between maps and teams the thing that holds a map back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of mapping holds its value in individuals and teams working out things and understanding. The question  of whether that’s using the brand colours, shapes or icons doesn’t impact that learning. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual similarity can also blur and make things harder to focus on. If you have lots of things looking the same, the detail can be lost. Particularly if you’re confronted with multiple journeys at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good maps and journeys find the right visual language for the thing they are trying to express. Or the model they’re exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such it’s important to find the colours, shapes and icons that help explain the immediate idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say you shouldn’t pay attention to the visual treatment of our maps. There are definitely times to think about your visual language. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example you might want to align when showing your bit fitting inside a coherent whole or aligning so multiple teams can show how things fit together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly you want to lean on existing things so that you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Borrow phases and structures that are well understood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empower and support teams to get on with mapping instead of visual treatments or debates about the visual style to take&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easier to communicate what you want to by borrowing what works elsewhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, no you shouldn’t force uniformity. But there are times when choosing patterns helps. Such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where teams are showing the detail of “their bit” but want it to be coherent or easy to fit within master or higher level maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where language or phases are well understood and some consistency helps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To stop needless creativity on what are internal specs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To empower and support teams to get on with mapping instead of visual treatments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you have varying levels of skills with the tools or techniques. Or having experience with tools that work differently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where you or teams have tried something and it didn’t work and that’s worth sharing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But rather than force teams to fit within a style that may or may not actually help model something, try working on how to share and make being consistent easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that. Work on how often and early teams share their models and blueprints. And where and how easy it is to find and work from other people’s things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href="https://www.duckworth.design"&gt;duckworth.design&lt;/a&gt; we’ve got a crude starter set of components and patterns as well as a treasure trove of things we’ve done before. Mostly it’s about visual treatments that helped communicate a certain thing or approaches to show user journeys, comments, issues or logic in a pathway that’s clear but not overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t force your teams to align visually. But do make it easier to do the right thing. And show what standards or approaches are expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it easy to start with tried and tested approaches. And get teams mapping and exploring things rather than focusing on unnecessary brand alignment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And ultimately make it easy to share back what they’ve found and do. So others can learn from them. Be that access to their maps, a set of starter templates or a more comprehensive library of approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
